Guide to the Fred R. Meyer Photographs circa 1905-1915
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Fred R. Meyer Photographs
circa 1905-1915
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 894
Meyer, Fred R., 1874-1939
2.0 linear feet 86 glass plate negatives
The Fred Meyer photograph collection contains 86 glass plate negatives, almost entirely of Native Americans, which likely date from around 1910. The collection was left in Browning, Montana by the photographer Fred Meyer. Although the collection is attributed to Meyer, it is evident that some of the plates are copies from other photographers. The majority of images are currently unidentified.
Biographical Note
Fred R. Meyer (1874-1939) was from Buffalo, New York. A butcher by trade, he was also known as an amateur photographer who traveled throughout the West between 1890 and 1915. According to the guide to the Fred R. Meyer photograph collection at the Smithsonian's National Museum of the American Indian Archive Center, "it has...been suggested that he was associated in some way (perhaps as a clerk) with the Indian agencies that served the Apsáalooke, Pikuni, and Numakiki reservations. He apparently also photographed in Pine Ridge in 1907 and collected objects in Wyoming and Montana."
This collection contains 86 glass plate negatives. The collection was apparently left by Fred Meyer with J. L. Sherburne or at the Sherburne Mercantile in Browning, Montana, possibly in 1908-1909 (though some images have later dates written on their envelopes). Although the collection is attributed to Fred Meyer, it is evident that some of the plates are copies of other photographs, and it is probable that some images were taken by other photographers. A small number of images have identification or dates written on the original negative sleeve, including identification of the subjects as Crow or Blackfoot, but it is not known who identified the images; the donor of the collection indicates the identifications may be inaccurate.
Images 894.001 through 894.028 are 5x7 plates. Images 894.029 through 894.045 are 8x10 negatives. Images 894.046 through 894.086 are smaller (usually 4x5) and many of these are or appear to be copies.
The collection was sorted by negative size and then the negatives were numbered.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
This collection is believed to have been in the custody of the Sherburne Family until it was transferred to William E. Farr.
The collection was given by William E. Farr to the University of Montana Archives and Special Collections in December 2016, along with a collection from the Sherburne Family.
The Smithsonian's National Museum of the American Indian Archive Center and the Buffalo Bill Center of the West each hold a collection of photographs by Fred R. Meyer.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Meyer, Fred R., 1874-1939--Archives
Montana--Photographs
Indians of North America--Montana--Photographs
Montana; Native Americans; Photographs
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; horse, tipi, man with headdress (Box-image 1/894.001)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; woman in beaded dress (Box-image 1/894.002)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; young male (Box-image 1/894.003)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; man with robe (Box-image 1/894.004)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; man with fringed sleeve (Box-image 1/894.005)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; man with war bonnet (Box-image 1/894.006)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; man sitting in chair (Box-image 1/894.007)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; man with war bonnet (Box-image 1/894.008)
- Sioux, Two Lance, Porcupine, South Dakota, 73 years old, circa 1905-1915 (Box-image 1/894.009)
- Sioux, Two Lance, Porcupine, South Dakota, 73 years old, circa 1905-1915 (Box-image 1/894.010)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; burial platform (Box-image 1/894.011)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; man with feathered headdress (Box-image 1/894.012)
- Sioux, Two Lance, Porcupine, South Dakota, 73 years old, circa 1905-1915 (Box-image 1/894.013)
- Sioux, Two Lance, Porcupine, South Dakota, 73 years old, circa 1905-1915 (Box-image 1/894.014)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; child with headdress (Box-image 1/894.015)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; man in Hudson Bay coat (Box-image 2/894.016)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; man carrying feathered fan (Box-image 2/894.017)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; woman with shell earring (Box-image 2/894.018)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; calvary horses with flag (Box-image 2/894.019)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; people with horses (Box-image 2/894.020)
- Blackfoot, Little Dog Tribe, circa 1905-1915 (Box-image 2/894.021)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; woman in jacket with painted nails (Box-image 2/894.022)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; man with interesting headdress (Box-image 2/894.023)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; family scene with tipi and cart (Box-image 2/894.024)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; faded, man with headdress (Box-image 2/894.025)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; picture faded (Box-image 2/894.026)
- Pine Ridge, circa 1905-1915; men on horseback (Box-image 2/894.027)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; man with hat and hand drum (Box-image 2/894.028)
- Crow, circa 1905-1915; men in field with two tipis (Box-image 3/894.029)
- Chippewa, 103 yrs old, circa 1905-1915 (Box-image 3/894.030)
- Blackfoot, circa 1905-1915; Blackfoot camp (Box-image 3/894.031)
- Blackfoot, circa 1905-1915; portrait of woman with robe (Box-image 3/894.032)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; portrait of man with medalian (Box-image 3/894.033)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; man on horse (Box-image 3/894.034)
- Blackfoot, Wades-in-Water, circa 1905-1915; portrait of man with painted dots on face (Box-image 3/894.035)
- Blackfoot, Montana, Albert Mad Plume, circa 1905-1915; portrait (Box-image 3/894.036)
- Crow, Three Bears, circa 1905-1915; portrait (Box-image 3/894.037)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; portrait of man with big headdress (Box-image 3/894.038)
- Blackfoot, Montana, circa 1905-1915; portrait of man (Box-image 3/894.039)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; portrait of man with headdress (Box-image 3/894.040)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; landscape with village, numerous painted tipis on prairie (Box-image 3/894.041)
- Crow, Three Bears, circa 1905-1915; portrait of man (Box-image 3/894.042)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; portrait of young woman (Box-image 3/894.043)
- Blackfoot, Chief Little Plume (Wolf Plume), circa 1905-1915; portrait (Box-image 3/894.044)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; man with hand drum (Box-image 3/894.045)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; braided hair? (Box-image 4/894.046)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; studio portrait of people (copy of photo) (Box-image 4/894.047)
- BAE photo [Bureau of American Ethnology], circa 1905-1915; portrait of man with breastplate (Box-image 4/894.048)
- BAE Photo [Bureau of American Ethnology], circa 1905-1915; portrait of man (Box-image 4/894.049)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; portrait of young man (Box-image 4/894.050)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; line of people in the distance on the prairie (Box-image 4/894.051)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; oration by chief? (Box-image 4/894.052)
- Red Cloud, circa 1905-1915; portrait (Box-image 4/894.053)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; totem pole? (clearly a copy negative) (Box-image 4/894.054)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; circle of men with their backs to camera. some wear western hats (Box-image 4/894.055)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; line of riders on prairie. Some in headdresses (Box-image 4/894.056)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; line of riders on prairie. Some in headdresses (Box-image 4/894.057)
- Flat Head's Sweat House, circa 1905-1915; man seated near structure (Box-image 4/894.058)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; line of riders (Box-image 4/894.059)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; line of riders. Negative envelope is dated 1913. (Box-image 4/894.060)
- Sitting Bull, Hunkpapa Dakota, circa 1905-1915; reproduction of cartes de visite from Spenser studio in Chicago (Box-image 4/894.061)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; chief orating (?) (Box-image 4/894.062)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; group of men and women in a circle (Box-image 4/894.063)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; sky and a cross (?) (Box-image 4/894.064)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; man sitting in front of a picket fence. buildings in background (Box-image 4/894.065)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; two men in front of picket fence (Box-image 5/894.066)
- Fred Meyer with other whites, circa 1905-1915; three white men standing on prairie. Tipis in background (Box-image 5/894.067)
- Fred Meyer (?), circa 1905-1915; in front of tipi (Box-image 5/894.068)
- Blackfoot parade, 1913, circa 1905-1915; line of riders. Tipis in background (Box-image 5/894.069)
- Jack Big Moon and Fred Meyer, circa 1905-1915 (Box-image 5/894.070)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; person seated (Box-image 5/894.071)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; looks like a big meeting in a shelter (Box-image 5/894.072)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; group of tipis with horses in front (Box-image 5/894.073)
- Little Bear, 1913, circa 1905-1915 (Box-image 5/894.074)
- Blackfoot parade, 1913, circa 1905-1915 (Box-image 5/894.075)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; People sitting on ground. In far background are tents. In very far background is a butte. (Box-image 5/894.076)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; large group of riders (Box-image 5/894.077)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; people in a line. Tipis and wagons in background. Looks like a ceremony (Box-image 5/894.078)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; young woman, seated, in elk tooth dress (Box-image 5/894.079)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; line of tipis, tents and wagons (Box-image 5/894.080)
- Little Bear, Cree, circa 1905-1915 (Box-image 5/894.081)
- Curly Bear, circa 1905-1915 (Box-image 5/894.082)
- Blackfoot Parade, 1913, circa 1905-1915 (Box-image 5/894.083)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; line of people walking. Mountains in background (Box-image 5/894.084)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; man with feathered headdress (Box-image 5/894.085)
- Untitled, circa 1905-1915; looks like a big meeting in a shelter (same as image 894.072) (Box-image 5/894.086)